What did the Battle of Cana actually
look like?
Modeling the Battle of Cana in true size
is a gargantuan undertaking.
A battle featuring one of the largest
Roman armies ever assembled, whose
frontage was so vast that it would take
over 40 minutes to walk across and so
deep that you could fit an entire soccer
field between the front and the rear
ranks.
Even Napoleonic artillery stationed at
one end of the field would lack the
range to reach more than half of the
army before it.
Such are the scales we are dealing with.
Without the benefit of a time machine,
this has long been left a mystery.
However, in this series, we leverage the
expertise of historians such as Dr.
Adrien Goldsworthy and the power of
tools like Unreal Engine 5 to bring the
past to life with the most detailed
simulation of this climactic battle ever
attempted.
From the often overlooked scale of the
city-sized camps which hosted the vast
armies assembled that day to the hours
long logistical nightmare of deploying
130,000 men from these camps into
formations on the field of battle
and the stunning blowby-blow phases by
which Hannibal managed the incredible
feat of enveloping and destroying an
army twice. ice his size.
We bring you back in time to experience
it all from both a bird's eyee
perspective in the skies above and the
boots on the ground in the thick of the
action. The skirmishers,
the cavalry,
the infantry,
and the generals.
The end result is a revolutionary new
way to not only visualize the massive
battles of antiquity, but to derive
novel academic conclusions which
challenge how we understand them. So
today, let's dive into this fascinating
simulation.
This is the true size of the battle of
Cana.
Hey everyone, it's Julian. Uh, no
sponsor segment here. I just wanted a
chance to speak to you humanto human for
a couple minutes. So, the video that
you'll watch today is very near and dear
to my heart. I've been making history
documentaries here on YouTube for over
10 years. And actually, 12 years ago is
one of my very first history
documentaries on the Battle of Cannai.
So, here we go full circle 12 years on.
Now, back in the day, I was heavily
inspired by the work of Adrien
Goldsworthy. He is my muse. He's the
reason why I got into history. very much
the way he made history approachable and
engaging is what inspired me to try and
do the same but in a video format. Now
when we were doing so early on I was
using Google Earth you know my primitive
use of Photoshop and then using heavily
the engine of Rome Total War. Now 12
years on I think we've shown in this
video leaps and strides how far we've
come. So on a technical side, you know,
Unreal Engine has been great to master,
especially with a team that I have
behind my back, dialing up that realism,
getting a lot closer to history, and
making it much more understandable,
approachable. We can do this POV stuff
that you'll enjoy. Another cool thing is
that my muse, Adrien Goldworthy, is no
longer just trapped in the book here,
but he's with us in the video. I got the
chance to, you know, speak to him,
collaborate with him, and so that's been
awesome to have him on the program for
me on a personal level. uh but then also
for him as well. You know, he's been,
you know, 10 years on, able to now
reflect more on his discoveries as a
researcher, as a historian, and shed new
lights and insight on this topic. So,
overall, you know, this video is sort of
quintessential in terms of what it means
for me to be on YouTube making these
documentaries. Now, we've done a lot
more stuff in the past and I hope to be
here 10 years on, but admittedly, we are
facing a lot of headwinds. You'll see
this across the YouTube space when it
comes to educational and history
channels when it comes to things like
AI. Uh what that means for production,
competition of viewer attention,
discoverability, how sponsors and money
gets thrown into the mix. Suffice to
say, we are in a tough spot. Uh myself
financially, we've been kind of
struggling on the channel. Uh so I've
never been one to really, you know, beg
for views, beg for money. Uh, I will
find ways to keep sustaining the channel
so that I can keep making these
documentaries and check in with you guys
10 years on. But I do want to say every
little bit does count. So, please
subscribe, like the video, become a
YouTube member, uh, join us on Patreon,
and especially, you know, just grab
something on our store. I made all these
little custom mugs that have history
memes built into them. I hope you'll
enjoy them. And we have some cool stuff
that we've commissioned over the years
from artists like this map of Carthage
that I have myself in my home that I
think you'll appreciate. So, no matter
what you choose to do, I can't thank you
enough for the support over the years.
Uh whether you've been watching us for
decades or for the last couple years or
even just in this video, thank you so
much for staying along, you know,
supporting humanmade work, supporting
history. And yeah, again, I can't thank
you guys enough. And enjoy the video.
I'll see you in the next one.
Modeling the Battle of Cana in true size
is a gargantuan undertaking.
While we shall be presenting our
reconstruction, other interpretations
exist. In acknowledgement of this fact,
it will be best to begin by describing
the key assumptions of our model.
First, we can begin in the abstract with
the army sizes
here. Palibius tells us that the Romans
deployed 16 legions, eight Roman and
eight allied, which in total numbered
80,000 infantry and roughly 6,000
cavalry.
Assuming an average distribution of
soldiers, we find that each legion has
5,000 men with the following breakdown
of troop types.
At the smallest level, this means each
century, with the exception of the
Triari, has on average 73 men, a roughly
20% increase over the 60 men who were
part of the usual muster.
Such inflated figures are in keeping
with the idea that the army had been
deliberately superersized by Rome in an
attempt to outmuscle Hannibal.
The cavalry, on the other hand, were
proportionately much smaller, consisting
of but 7.5% of the total troop count.
This was due to recent losses and the
difficulty of finding sufficient mounts
on such short notice.
Breaking out these riders, we have
assumed each Roman legion musters 10 tur
of 30 troopers for a total of 2,400
cavalry. This leaves us with a remainder
of 3,600 for the Allies, which roughly
tracks with Livy's sources claiming the
Allies had provided twice as many
horsemen. The entire force is under the
command of consoles Paulus and Varro
with command alternating each day.
On the Carthaginian side, Palibius tells
us that Hannibal deployed 40,000
infantry and 10,000 cavalry, making
their size 58% that of the Romans.
Beyond this, we have but informed
speculation to go on.
Based on accounts of prior battles in
the campaign, we shall assume the
following distribution of infantry
units.
Though greatly outnumbered by their
Roman equivalents, these are well
seasoned veteran troops who have also
been able to upgrade their gear through
the spoils of victory.
As for the cavalry, we will assume 4,000
are GIC, 2,000 are Iberian, and 4,000
are Numidian.
In this singular category, does Hannibal
actually outnumber his foe with 66% more
riders?
This will prove to have grave
consequences.
Taken altogether, we see that there are
in total
136,000 troops accounted for. an
insanely large army, which was even more
numerous when we consider the likely
presence of thousands more support
forces and camp followers. Now, let us
transport the armies to the battlefield
of Cana.
But to do so requires knowing exactly
where that is. It's a rather thorny
issue for any attempted recreations of
the battle. To offer insight on this
matter, we can now turn to Dr. Adrien
Goldsworthy.
>> The sources for Canai are pretty good
for a battle in the ancient world, and
we can narrow down the location fairly
well. We know where the ancient town of
Cannai was. Beyond that, everything gets
a little bit more difficult. Our best
sources tell us about the orientation of
the armies in relation to the river
Afidius.
The problem is that this river is on a
wide fairly flat plane and moves moves
regularly. I visited the site when I was
doing research for my books in the late
'9s. I took with me all the maps I could
find from various uh scholarly analyses,
some of them dating back to the 19th
century, some of them 20th century. I
also had a modern Italian uh road map of
the area scale as I could find. And when
I came there, the first thing that
struck me was that a the river was in a
different position on each of these
maps, but also the river I could see in
front of me on that um summer's
afternoon was again on a different line
to all the maps that I had. It just
emphasized how much the river moves
across this flood plane. Which then
means that trying to understand if as I
argue the battle did occur between the
river and the hill on which the town of
Canai stood just how much space there
was. How wide was this plane and was it
possible that you could actually fit
these very large armies into that space.
So there are lots of problems with canai
that nature doesn't help with. There
hasn't been any archaeology that we
could really establish the battlefield
even if that's possible. You have to be
lucky to find the right things. There
are to there's talk of earlier finds,
but they may be confused with medieval
battles fought near there as well. We
can't narrow down where the river was in
216 BC. So, there's a lot of guesswork
involved, which is why
looking in this way and mapping in this
way and doing everything to scale is
absolutely invaluable. So, I argue for
the battle being fought between the
river and the hill on which the town of
Cannai stands. This would mean that this
is in a very confined space.
At the most, we're talking about a width
of about 3 kilometers from the hill to
the river. Um, so is it the maximum 3 km
for a battle line? That's assuming they
go straight at sort of 90° between the
two. If there's more of an angle, then
things are different. Um, so this would
mean that this was a very dense,
crowded, narrow battlefield. For me,
that makes sense. The day before the
Romans had declined an offer of battle
from Hannibal to the north of the river.
Now the land there is very open. There
are no features on which to rest your
flanks. There's a lot more space.
Hannibal's got better cavalry than the
Romans. He's got more of it than the
Romans. In previous battles, those
cavalry have swept around the flanks and
enveloped the Roman line. So the Romans
know they don't want that to happen. The
Romans have got tons of infantry. Their
infantry has done well has broken
through the center at Trebia, at
Trazamini. So for me it makes sense.
Fight somewhere narrow and restricted
where although you won't be able to
deploy your numbers initially to the
full, nevertheless they can't be
outflanked, the great strength of your
army is protected and you deliver a
sledgehammer blow straight at the middle
of Hannibal's line. So for me that makes
sense and the fact that it is narrow is
actually an argument in favor rather
than argument against it.
On the other hand, some scholars have
argued that well this is far too narrow
and of course depending on where the
river actually was. You might not have 3
km, you might not have 2 km, you might
have even left in which case the
arguments for this become less and less
likely. They've tended to position it to
the south of the town or to the east of
the hill with the town so that you still
have the river on the same flanks of the
army, but there is much more open
country. There's nothing really to
anchor the Roman left, the Carthaginian
right in the same way that you're
between a river and a hill if you're in
the other position.
This has the advantage of space. There's
plenty of room for everybody.
Disadvantages of this, however, one is
that um why fight here? How is this
different from the land north of the
river where there's plenty of open
space? So why would the Romans be
willing to fight here when they hadn't
been willing to fight somewhere else?
And why bothered across the river? You
could have just challenged for battle on
the north bank if that's what you wanted
to do where Hannibal had offered it
before.
The other thing is when I visited the
site, I walked back having um got a lift
down to to Cannai. I walked back cuz I
wanted to look at this ground and the
there is a very clear very definite
slope down from the hill around Cannai
towards the coast. So if you had
deployed in this area, one thing is that
the Carthaginian deployment and where
the units were would have been more
obvious to see because they would be
deployed up a slope and any troops
behind in reserve hidden like the
Libyans would have been easier to see
perhaps. I mean again um you could argue
about that. The other thing is the
Romans would have been attacking uphill
and even a slight advantage like this on
a fairly gentle slope is something that
ancient armies take great trouble to
avoid. So for that reason I don't I just
don't buy this but it's not a case that
you can prove either way and again
coming to test things is okay with this
number of people in this sort of
formation how much space do they take
that's the great advantage of
experiments like this
>> as you can see even the foremost
historians on the matter are unable to
draw definitive conclusions given the
results of our upcoming simulations on
the army formations we find it more
probable that the battle took place
along the eastern plains. But regardless
of the exact placement of the armies,
many of the observations from this
simulation of Ka will apply to either
hypothesis.
With that being said, let us now
proceed.
Given the aforementioned uncertainties
of the exact battle lines, we are lucky
to at least be able to work off the
known location of the town of Cana,
whose ruins can still be seen today.
This is where we will begin our tour.
It is late July in 216 BC.
The hot summer sun beats down upon the
dry lands of Apulia as the seasonal
Volterus blows in from the south.
Where Roman farmers once ruled these
lands, now Hannibal is their master.
Over the past few weeks, the great Punic
general has laid claim to the site
whilst campaigning in the Apulia region
of southern Italy as part of his daring
invasion of Roman territory during the
Second Punic War.
The town of Cana itself holds strategic
value as a large supply depot with a
defensible position at top a ridgeline
hill. As you can see, it has a
commanding view of the surrounding
plains, which are filled with open
farmland.
Also of note is the Orphodus River to
the north, which lazily winds its way
across the gently sloping landscape
towards the coast of the Adriatic Sea,
some 8 km to the northeast.
Though Hannibal controls the town, his
army is too large to fit inside. Thus,
he initially sets up camp outside,
likely at top the nearby high ground.
From here, he can still survey the area
whilst also maintaining ready access to
the river from which he can draw fresh
water for thirsty men and horses. Within
a few days, he observes dust clouds to
the north from the vast Roman army,
which has been shadowing his every move.
Setting off in this direction, we see
that several kilometers away, the
consoles have established their own camp
on the opposite side of the river.
Here they too can draw from its waters
to refresh the troops.
Circling the camp, we can marvel at its
immense size. Housing over 100,000 men,
each side of its perimeter easily
measures over a kilometer across. This
is a city on the move. The sheer scale
means that it cannot stay in one place
for long without suffering supply
issues.
Thus, to mitigate these problems and to
secure access to the river, a second
smaller camp is built on the other side
of the Orphodus.
But such measures can only delay the
inevitable.
Soon the consoles will have to relocate
either to engage the Carthaginians or to
continue avoiding them.
Hannibal is well aware of this fact and
wants a fight on this ground. To press
the issue, he now moves his camp to the
same side of the river as the main Roman
position.
Doing so would have taken the greater
part of a day.
Flying to this new camp, we see that it
is somewhat smaller than that of the
legions, but no less impressive in size.
It too remains tethered to the river and
must deal with issues of supply.
Thus, as both sides now face off, they
are up against a logistical ticking
clock. But who will make the first move?
Historically, scenarios such as this
evolve into a psychological game between
generals.
Naturally, both sides wish to fight with
the most advantages stacked up on their
side before committing to an engagement.
A large factor to consider is that each
army has already dug in and will be at
an advantage if the foe is forced to
charge into their defenses. But on the
flip side, to remain passive in this
manner betrays a lack of confidence both
to the enemy and to one's own soldiers.
This can be even more important as
morale, after all, is what can win or
lose a fight.
Thus, commanders will often deploy
troops in the open ground as a
performative offering of battle.
How far forward such battle lines are
drawn is an additional barometer of an
army's confidence.
In this case, it is Hannibal who first
offers battle on August 1st.
Paulus, supposedly the more cautious of
the two Roman consoles, holds command
and refuses out of an apparent fear that
the open ground here will be to the
great advantage of the enemy's more
numerous cavalry.
Hannibal capitalizes on this morale
boost with another ploy to gain an
advantage.
He now sends the Numidians across the
river to chase off Roman foragers.
Despite the nearby presence of both
camps, they are impotent to prevent the
harassment.
It is another humiliating blow to the
legions.
Thus, as the more impetuous consular
prepares to take command the following
day, he has been sufficiently goaded to
make an aggressive counter move.
At dawn on the 2nd of August 216 BC, a
red vexelum is raised outside the tent
of Commander Varro. This is a
traditional signal that battle is to be
given.
However, we must imagine that the troops
had more advanced notice than to wake up
to such a sign.
Orders would have been distributed the
night before to the military tribunes
and the prefecty of the ari whose job it
was to disseminate the command down the
ranks and to supervise its execution.
Thus, as the sun rises, it lights upon
the massing ranks of infantry formations
already assembling into their unit
columns along the open ground of the
interval.
From here they will be guided out one
behind the other in a procession leading
out to the battlefield.
As the great coiled snake of the Roman
army slowly unfurs, its immense size is
evident by the laborious nature of the
process.
Arranged in column, it takes each legion
roughly half an hour to simply leave the
camp.
Thus, with two camps spilling forth
simultaneously from their main gates, we
can approximate that it will take the 16
legions around 2 to 4 hours to fully
emerge when accounting for bottlenecks
and other delays.
From here, their multic long bodies will
slither into position, trampling through
fields and splashing through waters.
At the same time, Hannibal keeps a close
watch on the Roman force.
With spies and perhaps even intercepted
deserters, he is informed of Consul
Varro's decision to offer battle.
Thus, as the direction of the enemy's
advance is revealed, the Punic commander
now directs his men to match course.
The offer for battle has been accepted.
Hannibal's army now emerges from its own
coils and slithers across the land. As
if to message his agreement to the
Romans, a massive plume of dust now
rises from the Punic camp.
From the perspective of an observer
miles away, it would appear as if the
two sides were deliberately coordinating
their intentions with smoke signals. But
as the vast dust clouds rise higher in
the skies and slowly advance towards one
another, it is clear that a showdown of
monumental proportions is about to take
place. This is all noted by observers
from Rome who ride back to the city to
report on such tidings. By the time they
arrive, the fate of Cana will already
have been determined.
But now let us race against the writing
of history to watch as it unfolds.
>> Along our battlefield, the units of
either side are moving into position. By
tradition, this takes place by first
sending out a screen of light troops to
cover the deployment of the main body.
At Cana, such a maneuver involves the
mobilization of some 25 to 30,000
skirmishers.
A prodigious amount of troops whose
numbers alone would rival the largest
battles of the medieval era.
Here they are but a holding force.
Behind the skirmisher screen, the battle
lines are drawn. This process involves
the army columns marching to the extreme
ends of the formation and falling into
line. It is a simple process of follow
the leader which can be executed by even
the most green troops. However,
regardless of simplicity, deployments of
this scale take time and it can be many
more hours before the last of the troops
trickle in.
From the ground level, it is entirely
unclear to any of the participants what
is going on beyond their immediate
vicinity. They must simply trust in the
process while officers ride back and
forth to coordinate the movements of a
blind Goliath.
Luckily for us, we can observe the
entire battlefield from above. This is a
view never experienced before and thus
never documented.
As a result, our presentation is
speculative reconstruction based on
vague myopically constrained sources.
For some insight into the nuances of
this reconstructive process, we can turn
once more to military historian Dr.
Adrien Goldsworthy.
Now, as is always the case with the
ancient world, we don't have too much
information about what was normal, what
was typical, whether there was a
standard formation for the manipul, or
whether it rather depended on
circumstances in the ground where you
were fighting. Um, but the suggestion
that they're many times deeper than
their wide rather suggests that that
wasn't true and that they were shallower
under normal circumstances.
Beyond that though, we don't have any
details. So just how narrow, how deep,
and how narrow were the gaps between
individual maniples. There's a whole
debate about the checkerboard formation
and whether the gaps between maniples
closed up when the fighting actually
began or not. Um but in this case
clearly the gaps are made significantly
smaller. Therefore there's less need for
that. There's less requirement for that.
Just how you do it would depend. And
remember
all of this is going to be guesswork. So
we assume that because he talks about
the the units which we normally
translate as maniples as being there you
kept with the normal trip xx a the three
lines of harti prinkabase and triari and
that each individual manipul was
narrower fronted deeper and closer
together with its neighbors on either
side and presumably the latins that are
on either flank in the ally are doing
much the same thing.
But again, precisely what that means,
most ancient authors assume we know this
sort of stuff. There's no need to tell
or explain. Therefore, they don't
bother. And the technical manuals, if
they existed, have not survived. So that
a lot of things we assume about ancient
warfare, you will often hear said, and
I've written it um that the the standard
depth, the typical depth for Greek
fallank was 8 deep. Um there's very
little evidence for that really very
very little and none at all for the
Roman army of this period as to just
what's going on
>> when it comes to reconstructing cana
specifically we have founded our model
upon the better understood dynamics of
the Roman army at a high level we are
confident from our sources that it
consists of the allied cavalry to the
east infantry in the center and the
Roman cavalry in the test.
Zooming in begins to reveal some of the
uncertainties.
The infantry, for instance, here
consists of just 14 legions with the
assumption that two entire legions have
been left behind in camp in keeping with
Palibius's claim that 10,000 troops were
held back to guard the baggage and
threaten the enemy's camp.
Zooming in closer, we see that the
individual legions still maintain their
multi-layered formation of infantry
tiers, but have arranged themselves in a
deep tight formation rather than the
more typical checkerboard pattern. This
is an interpretation of Palibius's
report that the maniples were quote
closer together than usual and many
times deeper than they were wide. Here
we have assumed a total legionary depth
of 50 men, though some scholars push
this to in excess of 70 men. In either
case, using standard troop spacing and
accounting for gaps between units, we
end up with a total depth of around 100
m for the heavy infantry.
This is an extremely unorthodox
formation in light of the fact that most
armies of the period drew up in files of
4 to 8 men or 10 to 20 m deep. The
reason being that while depth improves
staying power, each added rank yields
diminishing returns. Any extra manpower
is better used to extend that unit's
width with which to outflank one's foe.
But at Cana, the Romans have more than
enough manpower to spare.
Already the infantry span almost 2 km in
width. By going deeper, the consoles
apparently wish to ensure that their
green troops are as insulated as
possible from morale shocks.
Dropping down to the ground perspective
of a soldier in the midst of this
formation, it is easy to see its
psychological advantages.
To all sides, one is surrounded by
comrades while the front lines are
nearly a soccer field away.
All this means that the vast majority of
Roman troops can expect to do nothing
more than stand in line and let the
sheer weight of their ranks brute force
its way to victory. If they are lucky,
they might catch a glimpse of the action
along the front.
Zooming back out, we can now turn our
attention to the cavalry. The nature of
their formations are even less well
understood as will be emphasized by Dr.
Goldsworthy.
>> When you come to cavalry, you have to
think in a very different way to
infantry and that's quite hard for us to
do because most of us don't necessarily
know much about horses. We're certainly
not used to horses in these sorts of
numbers. You don't see thousands of
cavalrymen anywhere in the world today.
So even the big parades and the
ceremonial units you have, you know,
they're not on that sort of scale. And
when movies have extras mounted, they
never have those sorts of numbers. And
of course, these days they'll be adding
lots of extra CGI horsemen. So the the
big blocks of Rohirim you see in the
Pelenor Fields and the Return of the
King movie, they look very visually
impressive, but that is not the way any
real cavalry would operate because the
whole point of cavalry is speed,
maneuverability,
uh movement. They are not like
infantrymen who will go forward and
perhaps best go forward slowly and then
sl it out with the enemy. They'll
charge, the enemy will run or they will
be chased back. You chase them till you
start to get scattered, you start to get
blown, they have reserves, then they
chase you back, your reserves chase them
back and so on. Ancient authors
characterize cavalry warfare as
incredibly fluid, back and forth, quite
hard to understand and exactly the same
pattern was still visible in the 18th
19th century. You can read about
Waterloo and it's exactly the same
there. That's the way lots of horses
behave. So, it's best not to think of
big big blocks similar to the infantry
when we come to cavalry. And probably
we're thinking more of troops,
squadrons, individual units forming
several lines but with large gaps
between them to allow this
maneuverability, to allow this
flexibility because you pack lots of
horses closely together and you're just
going to end up with a big stampede
either forward or backwards. but
something you can't control. You witness
the defeat of the Pompeian cavalry at
Farcelus where several thousand of them
are stampeded by a relatively small
number of infantry. They can't recover
from that. And the less trained the
horses are, the more important it is to
keep them in separate blocks and
separate units because they just get
excited and they they're inclined to run
in the same direction as everybody else.
So you have to think of groups of 30 men
like the Roman Turma, 40, 50, 100, maybe
200 units like that, but lots of them
and in more than one line. And that's a
very different way of thinking about how
these will be deployed to our standard
nice little rectangle on a map where
this represents 500, 1,000, 5,000 men.
With cavalry in particular, you
shouldn't think that way for infantry,
but with cavalry, it's fatal to think
that way. They need lots more space.
Palibius talks about cavalry men
requiring double the amount of frontage
that infantry of the same numbers would
require, but it's not quite as simple
as, oh, there's a, you know, you just
spread them out and each cavalryman
requires twice the space. It's the units
require space around them. So that's
what mattered. We've got to think of
lots of little blocks, a little bit like
some of those 17th century woodcuts and
engravings of English Civil War battles
and that sort of thing.
With these ideas in mind, our model
assumes that the Roman cavalry are
compactly deployed in their 30men ti
with separation between rows of units to
allow for the more fluid engagement of
mounted troops. As such, their frontage
is about 600 m across and 70 m deep.
Flipping to the other side, we can now
examine the disposition of the
Carthaginians. Here there is very little
precedent to draw upon for their
reconstruction. Thus, our model largely
relies on matching the width of their
Roman counterparts and adding depth to
reach the troop counts given to us by
our sources.
Namely, this includes the roughly 4,000
Numidian cavalry under Hano on the
eastern flank, GIC and Iberian cavalry
under Hazdrabal on the western flank,
and the 35,000 infantry under Hannibal
and Maggo in the center. Of this last
group, we have assumed that
approximately 5,000 troops have been
left back at camp to counter Rome's own
10,000 troops which were siphoned off to
threaten their baggage train.
Diving deeper, we can now explore the
infantry.
It is here that Hannibal uses the
non-punic troops to form his famous
cresant at the start of battle.
Typical media depictions tend to
overexaggerate its shape without
accounting for the practicalities of
such a formation.
In reality, it is likely that the battle
line consisted of an eclectic mix of
small war bands of around 200 to 500
men, which were arranged in echelon, one
next to the other.
In theory, each unit might advance
further out than its neighbor to
increase the overall boeing of the line.
However, they would have been hesitant
to advance too far and expose their
flanks.
Thus, by assuming that each unit
overlaps significantly with its
neighbor, our model results in a cresant
with a maximum depth of a mere 85 m at
the center.
Given that the frontage of the infantry
is almost 2 km across, this is an
exceptionally shallow cresant.
Such a finding begins to cast doubt on
traditional understandings regarding the
purpose and function of the cresant at
Cana.
This should be discussed further when we
simulate the actual combat along this
front.
For more thoughts on the matter, we can
turn once more to Dr. Goldsworthy.
Anything that's unique is always harder
to study because there aren't parallels.
And there's nothing quite like this. You
know, there've been various theories
that the naval battle of Ecnomomas had
similar tactics to Canai and all this
sort of thing, but none of them really
hold any any water or any weight. They
just don't don't make sense. It's better
to see this not as a plan that Hannibal
had had in the back of his minds for
years and oh, I've got this cunning
idea, but something tailored to his army
in relation to the Roman army and where
he was fighting and the circumstances of
that battle and the buildup to it, the
campaign, something that's right for
today and will work for today because
he's not doing the same thing elsewhere.
And he doesn't try and do this again
anywhere else. So that means it's
difficult. The probability is that this
is rather less dramatic and shallower
than many diagrams will show. But then
diagrams need to emphasize. So just what
was necessary. The point clearly is that
Hannibal wishes the very center of his
line to get into contact before other
parts of it. So the very central unit is
advanced some distance. We don't know
how far. You know, is it 10 m, 100 m
more, whatever it might be. Again, this
is something that the model can test
very, very well and give us an idea of
what this would look like. But a lot
depends on how people would behave. So
he wants the Romans to make contact
there first. Is that in the expectation
the rest of the Roman line will stop
while that's being fought and until
they're pushed back? Is it that this
will start to make the Roman line more
ragged as they begin to come forward? Uh
that some might attack, start their
charge, start their volley of missiles
at a a greater distance. We'll come on
to all of this later, but it it's
difficult to know precisely what
Hannibal intends. So, it's all a
question of experimenting. It's bound to
be shallower than the Roman formation
because you're covering the same
frontage as a far more uh numerically
superior force of Romans. There's a lot
of Romans out there. You're trying to
match their frontage. But that also
means that it's much less dense as to
what's going on. There's more space for
not just individual units to act and
react and support each other, move back,
backwards and forwards depending on how
the fighting is going, but also for
officers, commanders to move around.
Having covered the formation of the
non-African infantry, we can now turn
our attention to the Libyans.
Our sources are unclear on their
deployment with Libby stating vaguely,
quote, "They were used to form the two
wings which had been drawn back."
Some depictions show them stacked in
deep columns.
But once more, we should question the
practicality of such exaggerated
deployments.
Working in true size, we see that there
is little benefit to having the units so
far back from the front.
At the scales we are working with, any
position they might adopt locally
results in the equivalent distance
required to move from the wings towards
the center or around the flanks for an
envelopment.
Thus, we have chosen to deploy the
Libyans at no greater depth than the
Legions, whose formation was already
considered overkill in terms of staying
power.
Ultimately, this seems to have been
their role in battle to hold as an
unbreakable bastion of elite troops that
could be mobilized when the time came to
strike at vulnerable Roman forces.
With this in mind, we can now turn to
the cavalry on the wings. To the east,
we find the Numidian light cavalry.
Here, we have modeled them as loosely
spaced units, which can easily maneuver
for evasive skirmishing against the
enemy. The end result is a formation of
equivalent numbers to the Roman allies
opposite them, but with a greater
overall footprint.
Meanwhile, on the western flank, we find
the GIC and Iberian cavalry. They number
about two and a half times that of the
Romans standing against them. The
severity of this mismatch is reflected
in our model by the idea that while they
might intend to fight as close order
cavalry, their great numbers have forced
them to separate into multiple groups to
preserve command and control and avoid
devolving into a stampeding herd.
Any one of these groups has sufficient
strength to greatly damage the Roman
cavalry on its own.
masked. In this way, though, the
combined might of the Carthaginians is
poised to absolutely flatten them.
Now that we have painstakingly laid out
our model of the armies at Cana, we can
take a step back to appreciate the
results of their true size. Based on our
assumptions, it measures over 3 km
across.
Let us now fly across the battlefield to
get a more visceral sense of the scales
involved.
For a more grounded approach, we might
even consider simulating a walk across
the battlefield.
But to do so would take roughly 40
minutes.
Even when simulating a horse making the
journey, it would take a rider around 5
minutes at full gallop to race from one
end to the other.
As a final measure of the battlefield's
size, we can now fire off a Napoleonic
cannon across its breadth.
As the shot arches across the
battlefield, it passes by endless ranks
of soldiers.
Even under the best conditions, the
cannon's maximum range will only get us
halfway across the field. The scales
here are simply unfathomable.
Given all this, we must marvel at what
it would have been like to experience
such an event where the scale of the
conflict stretches from horizon to
horizon.
For soldiers, at least they can be
resigned to focusing on the more
comprehensible scope of their immediate
surroundings.
Leaders on the other hand are afforded
no such luxury.
The burden of command demands that
generals and their officers must somehow
remain apprised of matters across the
entire front.
>> It's going to be very hard for anybody
to see all of it. It's a big army.
You're on a fairly flat plane. Um you
don't have a vantage point. Your two
senior commanders, your consoles, each
choose to command one of the cavalry
wings to keep those in the fight as long
as possible so that the center can win.
Once they're there, they can't see very
much beyond the area immediately around
them. They can see the enemy, but they
can't see much more than that. One of
the big drawbacks of reducing the gaps
between the maniples, making the
maniples deeper, but packing everybody
into that space is that there is less
room for staff officers, senior officers
and their um support staff to ride
around the formation, to ride amongst
the Roman line. It's much harder to get
around. It's also harder to see
anything. So, the command and control
element is a problem right from the very
start. But again, it comes back to this.
We've got a simple plan. All we've got
to do is go forward and eat our way into
the enemy line. In contrast to the
Romans, Hannibal has a rather more
conventional battle line. Yes, it's got
the crest and everything, but in terms
of the depth of formations, how densely
packed they are, there's no indication
he's trying to match the Romans by
cramming everybody in. His formations
are relatively shallow in comparison to
the Romans. There'll be intervals
between the units. Not just, you know,
we can see that by the fact that he
alternates and Gauls in the center of
the line. These are clearly distinct
units with some sort of space between
them. That means that he and his brother
and any other senior officers can see
better what's going on, but can also
move around. They can ride between
units. They can ride along the battle
line. They can ride behind them. they
can get to close to most of those units
and talk to them, encourage them, set an
example in a way that is much, much more
difficult for the Romans in their far
more crowded, dense formation.
>> All of this takes place in the calm
before the storm. From here on out, the
descent into the maddening true size of
Cana has only just begun.
It's midday on the 2nd of August 216 BC
and the largest Roman army yet assembled
has finally finished deploying for
battle at Cana.
Opposite them stands the far smaller
army of Hannibal Barker.
What is about to transpire will go down
as one of the most famed and studied
battles of history. But never before has
it been simulated to this level of
detail.
From fleshing out the unrecorded
skirmishing action which occupied the
bulk of the morning's action to the
messy realities of marching 70,000
infantry through obstacle strewn
farmland into the teeth of an echelon
battle line.
The clashing of the cavalry across two
wildly different engagements.
the maneuvering of troops in each phase
of the ensuing battle
and the final envelopment of the Roman
army in what would prove to be one of
the single bloodiest days of battle in
history.
We bring it all to life from both a
bird's eyee perspective and the boots on
the ground. This is the climactic
conclusion of the battle of Cana.
On the 2nd of August 216 BC, a red
vexalum waved outside the tent of consul
gas Varro.
After days of posturing across the
plains of Cana, it was finally time for
battle. But even such a simple matter
would take hours for the tens of
thousands of troops to be led out of
their camps and onto the battlefield.
As both armies deployed for battle,
their 3 km fronts were screened by a
mass of skirmishes numbering some 28,000
troops in total. An incredible host in
its own right whose assembled ranks
would have dwarfed most battles of the
medieval era.
On the Roman side came the 20,000 vels,
a class of young poor levies equipped
with simple javelins, small shields and
animal skin caps.
Unlike the heavy infantry, they do not
appear to have adopted any rigid
formation or been accompanied by any
formal officer rank. Thus, they deployed
as a loose swarm with relative autonomy
over their area of the battlefield.
However, it is likely that some guidance
was needed to coordinate their actions.
Thus, we have assumed that the bands of
Vel remain relatively close to their
parent manipul. This would have given
them several hundred meters worth of
buffer, enough separation to perform
screening actions, but close enough to
fall back to the bastion of heavy
infantry if pressed too heavily.
Bridging this gap will likely have been
runners or mounted messengers meant to
maintain some level of coordination
between the two groups.
These presumably prowled the rear lines
of the Vel, keeping tabs on their ranks
and peering over their heads in an
attempt to glean some sense of the
enemy's disposition.
Opposite them stand their Carthaginian
counterparts.
At just 8,000 strong, they number less
than half that of the Romans.
Yet what they may lack in quantity, they
more than make up for in experience.
Among these ranks stand not poor young
boys, but mature specialists, which
include the Libyan Lancori,
the Iberian Krati, and the Bleeric
Svenoni.
Most are armed with bundles of javelins
and small round shields. Yet, it is the
last of these groups which would prove
most formidable.
Compared to the rest of the skirmishers,
which largely relied on short range
weapons, these professional mercenaries
wielded long range slings capable of
loosing lead bullets at speeds of over
100 km an hour and ranges of up to 400
m.
Thus, as the two skirmishing bodies
drifted close to one another, they were
poised for an incredibly asymmetrical
clash.
But how exactly such fights occurred is
left a mystery, as their details are
rarely documented by our sources.
We must imagine that these were rather
fluid in nature. Each battle line, after
all, was composed of a loose swarm whose
members would surge in and out of no
man's land as packs or as individuals.
To better conceptualize these dynamics,
we can focus in on a small region of the
front. Here, across a space no larger
than a soccer field, are faced off 100
youths and 40 adults.
Yet unlike a friendly game which might
take place at the school sporting event,
now both sides are armed with deadly
weapons with no rules or referees to
curb the violence.
For the Veletes, this was reportedly a
time to show one's courage in battle
before comrades and superiors.
Joining them on the front lines, we see
what it might have looked like to step
forth into the fray. Here we observe a
mass of the enemy before us just beyond
the reach of our weapons.
To strike them will require leaving the
safety of our ranks.
In a fit of courage, a young soldier
might dash out to taunt the foe, dancing
between incoming salvos and toss their
own javelin before pulling back.
Others might more timidly emerge to
collect spent weapons on the ground or
pass them ahead to the more deserving.
Likewise, the enemy does the same.
Though with greater strength and
practiced accuracy,
as this dance is repeated over the early
hours of battle, we must imagine that
rivalries would have formed as each
group of skirmishers tested itself
against the other across their slice of
the battlefield.
In areas where both sides are armed with
javelins, perhaps there would have been
a relative balance between the more
numerous Roman youths and the more
experienced Carthaginian adults.
In other areas, perhaps a slight
advantage was gained by one side or the
other due to some particulars of the
terrain or as injuries and deaths began
to take their toll on the morale of the
participants.
Yet now imagine what would have happened
in areas where these same groups of
javelinar armed vel were matched against
the professional slingers of the
Balieric Isles. Here the youths would
have been met with the ancient
equivalent of gunfire. Lead bullets
fired at extreme range with such force
that it could pierce armor and such
accuracy that it could reportedly target
individual parts of the face. The
ensuing carnage is left to our
imagination.
Of our two primary sources, Libby is
mute on the matter while Palibius merely
remarks, quote, "The affair between
these lightarmed troops was indecisive."
Clearly this skips over the very real
life or death struggles which transpired
in the earliest hours of the battle of
Cana.
But without further information, we must
move on.
At some points, the skirmishing phase
was called off by the waving of banners
and the blaring of trumpets. Likely this
occurred as the last of the heavy
infantry and cavalry had reached their
designated places in the battle line. By
now, it would have been close to midday
with the sun beating down on the
sweating brows of over 120,000 idling
soldiers. The heat and their nerves left
them dripping with anticipation to get
this over with.
Soon, this wish would be granted by the
commanders who deemed it time for the
battle to begin in earnest.
Our sources claim that it was Hannibal
who made the first move, sending forth
his 10,000 cavalry against the Roman
flanks. This would have begun at a walk
or slow trot so as to maintain stamina
and unit cohesion. Thus, crossing the
roughly half kilometer separating the
armies would have taken around 3 to 5
minutes.
For a better idea of what this may have
looked like, we can zoom in. Beginning
on the western flank
here, the hooves of 6,000 GIC and
Iberian horses kick up large plumes of
dust into the air.
It is an impressive force whose sheer
size has forced them to break out into
multiple waves of assault and reserve
units just to squeeze into the narrow
battlefield between the infantry and the
river.
When these units get closer to the
Romans, the first of their ranks will
begin to pick up speed. Officers shout
encouragement to their squadmates, while
steeds vocalize their own emotions to
the herd.
As momentum builds, each individual is
now swept along in a growing avalanche,
enveloped by deafening sound and
blinding dust.
To participate in such a charge must
have been an incredible rush of
adrenaline.
The more than twice outnumbered ranks of
the equites have taken a defensive
posture alongside the river.
>> Do not concern yourself with those
Carthaginians yonder.
Few will be honest sons of Carthage if
there is such a thing. Carthaginians,
cowards all, pay others to die for them.
Let us give them death.
>> Livy's account claims that around this
time, the consulus dismounted after
being wounded by a slinger, leading many
other Romans to do the same. Though this
is not backed up by other sources, it
does perhaps preserve some tradition of
cavalry having chosen to fight on foot
in an attempt to bolster their static
position.
Whatever the case, it seems clear that
the Romans were indeed aware that they
were doomed to be defeated on this
flank. It was just a matter of delaying
the inevitable as long as possible for
the infantry to win the day.
To get a true sense of things, we can
drop down to the front lines. Here, the
coming of the Carthaginians is heralded
by rising dust clouds and the crescendo
of hoof beatats.
Soon this is followed by the haunting
appearance of a dark line rolling
swiftly over the countryside.
For a soldier in the center of
formation, observing this horizon
spanning avalanche of flesh and iron
will have shaken them to the core.
The dire nature of Rome's predicament is
only further reinforced as we zoom out
to see that beyond this first wave of
Carthaginians are two more great waves
of death hurtling towards them.
To make matters worse, we are told by
Palibius that unlike typical cavalry
engagements, quote, "There was none of
the usual formal advance and retreat.
But when they once got to close
quarters, they grappled man to man and
dismounting from their horses fought on
foot.
In our model, we have depicted this as a
literal smashing together of the front
ranks. From a distance, this is
relatively easy to conceptualize as it
aligns with the way such engagements are
typically shown in games and movies.
However, it proves far harder to imagine
the realities on the ground. Here would
have been a roughly 500 meter wide
rolling mass of man and beast. Unlike
the infantry blocks which can be
expected to have some level of rigidity
in their fighting, the cavalry were
entirely more fluid given the inherent
nature of being mounted upon animals.
In some cases, man and horse worked
together to fight with some semblance of
coordination.
Other times, a rider was at the mercy of
their steeds unpredictable motions.
All the while, slashes, stabs, and
javelin throws were being exchanged.
Brute force even had its place as riders
reportedly resorted to physically
dragging each other off the saddle.
On the ground would have been strewn the
carnage of trampled men, crippled
horses, spent weapons, and dismounted
troops who now waded through the mayhem.
Understandably, the fighting would have
been brutal.
Our sources claim that the Romans fought
with great spirits and determination.
However, the numerical odds was stacked
heavily against them. It was only a
matter of time before the crushing might
of the Carthaginians broke through.
But for now, let us pivot over to the
eastern flank.
Here we find an entirely different
dynamic at play. On this front, the
Carthaginians have deployed the 4,000
Numidian light cavalry.
Specializing in hitand-run tactics.
These troops will have surged out
towards the Roman line in nimble
squadrons. Once in range, they then
loosed their javelins before wheeling
about.
From the Roman perspective, this would
not have been as immediately deadly as
the brutal charge on the western flank.
Yet, it was nonetheless extremely trying
on the nerves.
The refusal of the enemy to come to
blows denied the equitates a chance to
relieve stress through violence.
Instead, they were subjected to an
incessant needling.
From a ground's eye view, we can see how
unnerving this would have been.
Yet, any attempt to break ranks and
chase after the Numidians would have had
the effect of chasing after a flock of
birds.
Lighter and faster, they simply darted
out of the way and into the unknown
dangers of the dust shrouded ground
beyond.
Over pursuing in such a situation would
have tired out one's steed and
potentially left Romans isolated. At
this point, Numidian squadrons would
have closed in to pick them off.
Such tactics would have been enabled by
the use of multiple self-reinforcing
ranks of reserves behind which
skirmishers could rally and relieve one
another.
In this way might the fighting be
dragged out for hours. Thus we see the
highly dynamic nature of the eastern
flank which slowly but inexraably sapped
the strength of the Romans.
As the fighting on the flanks occurred,
it was now the turn of the Romans to
take the offensive by advancing their
main body of heavy infantry. Once more,
it should be emphasized that even such a
seemingly simple maneuver was made
complex by the sheer scale of the task
at hand. After all, we are talking about
coordinating the actions of 70,000
individuals across a roughly 2 km wide
front.
For more on the matter, we can turn to
historian Adrien Goldsworthy.
>> Once you've got your army in position,
you also have to once you're ready,
decide to order it forward. We don't get
any specifics about this. We assume that
it's done by signal um in that you have
trumpets blowing standards perhaps moved
the commander standard moved in a
particular way or maybe just the the
trumpet signal that is then taken up by
trumpeters along the line and everybody
goes. Um it's probably not as neat and
everyone stepping off at exactly the
same time on the same foot sort of
thing. Again, this is a a big
inexperienced army bigger than anything
the Romans have ever known before. So
nobody really knows how to do things.
You're trying to modify your normal
practices as little as possible to keep
everybody understanding what's going on.
Um in later periods in the 1st century
BC, we here at uh Philippi, Brutus sends
out dispatch riders to give the order to
advance to all the different elements of
his army. And as a result, various
legions, each one goes when it gets the
order and just heads off so that the
ones that nearest to him get theirs
first and start the attack first and the
others come in later. And you know,
clearly his staff of this fairly amateur
civil war army had not worked out that
this was uh likely to to happen. Um at
Fapsus, one of Caesar's battles where
the advance begins without his
instruction. Caesar was trying to stop
them and one cohort persuades, forces
its trumpeter, its Cornic to signal the
order to advance and starts going and
then the order is taken up. Everybody
repeats the signal and everybody goes
and Caesar is supposed to said, "All
right, fair enough. Let's get on with it
and attack." So even with the more
professional armies of that period,
admittedly in a civil war situation, you
could get moments of confusion. So, it's
again, we've got these nice digital
figures representing our our Roman
soldiers, but remember, everybody's an
individual. Everybody's a human being,
and this is not the most experienced
Roman army around.
But if the start of an advance was
already messy, the march itself proved
even more so. This had much to do with
the inherent variability of the
participants, the terrain, and the
conditions. For much of our model, we
have been forced to simplify such
variables.
But in this section, we shall attempt to
dial up the realism to give you a better
idea of the real experience. Here, Dr.
Goldsworthy shall once more be our
guide.
As the Romans move forward, their
formations will start to decay at least
to some extent. Important thing to
remember is that even though Canai is
fought in what we consider to be a flat
plane in that there are no major terrain
features recorded in our sources or
obvious from the ground today and that's
true wherever it takes place whichever
of the theories is followed
that real landscapes particularly
farmland are not like carefully moan
football pitches or bowling greens or
anything like that. This is real land,
so it won't be perfectly flat. There
will be little undulations. There'll be
little humps and bumps. Because it's
farmland, people have been using this.
There's going to be tracks. There's
going to be walls. There's going to be
boundary stones. There are going to be
perhaps hedges, trees, vines in places.
We don't know what was being grown there
at the time of the battle. What the um
but there could be animal pens. There
could be drainage ditches. All of these
things. And you know people being very
clear farmers marking out this is mine,
this is yours and that's the boundary
you don't cross. So all of these things
will mean that not everybody is going to
be going at a perfectly steady regular
pace straight forward. People will tend
to veer a bit to the right, a bit to the
left. Some groups will move faster than
others. You get the very keen officer
who's urging people forward and always
half anticipates goes too soon. The
other who's a bit sluggish, who's a bit
slower, bit more cautious. Um, so the
little bits of the micro landscape in a
sense that we can't represent. We've got
no chance at all even if we locate the
battlefield knowing what this was and
would never appear in an account by a
Palibius or Olivia or anyone like this
because it it mattered to the dozen or
so men who were marching along that bit
of frontage and those behind them. It
doesn't matter to anybody else. Many
people would never know it was there at
all. You know, there might be the odd
building out there, the odd hut as well.
Who knows what was there? um fences,
anything, you know, lots of things like
this. So, it's going to get messy fairly
quickly. This is human nature. Added to
the stress of all this, you are
advancing towards an enemy that you can
see and that is waiting to kill you or
perhaps soon coming forward to kill you.
And even however keen you are, this is
still, you know, a pretty nervous moment
for anyone with all the excitement, the
noise, the the hubbhub of all those
people and the sense of again being with
this army is probably the time when
you're seeing more human beings in any
one place than you ever have before.
When that army raises its battle cry,
it's probably louder than anything
you've heard in your life before,
particularly for many of the Romans and
the less experienced ones. So this is a
very novel situation. As the Romans
advance, there isn't a great deal that
their officers can do. The consoles are
off on the flanks. Um the
centurions,
two with each maniple in theory, six
tribunes with a legion. They can
influence the men immediately around
them. Uh anyone who can hear their voice
and then is willing to listen to it.
It's mainly a question. They can try and
keep the pace steady. They can try and
stop people from surging forward too
quickly, breaking up formation even
faster than it's it's going to happen.
They can try and encourage them. They
can try and cheer them. Palibius talks
about the Roman lines, Roman troops
regularly advancing, cheering and
banging their weapons against their
shields. So if you've got that sort of
noise, then it's all the harder for
officers to compete with that, for
trumpet signals to compete with that.
But again, think of the volume you might
get from the crowd at a sporting event,
the the cheering, the chanting you can
have. It's that sort of volume of noise.
So the Romans can't do a lot apart from
keep everybody moving forward, try and
keep them in some sort of order and
fairly steady, but they're not doing
anything very, very clever. And there
are limits. Again, comes back to this
dense formation that's going to be
deteriorating even further. For anyone
on horseback that gives them a bit of a
viewpoint higher than everyone else,
it's going to be hard to move around the
battle line because there's not the
space there would normally be between
maniples even in the approach to combat.
So all of these things restrict what
they can do, but they can certainly
encourage each other and try and keep
things reasonably steady. In contrast,
the Carthaginian commanders have a more
normal deployment. Hannibal, his brother
Mgo, who's there in the center of the
line, they can ride around. They can
ride between the units. They can ride up
to them. They can encourage the men that
um they want to as far as they can in
terms of the ability to speak the
languages of the different units
involved. The Aberians in particular
have been, you know, serving for a long
time under Hannibal and his family. So,
they're men. He knows well. He probably
can communicate with them. The Gauls
have been with him for less than two
years. But again, that's, you know, um a
time to build up some sort of
relationship.
So, they can do more, they can see more.
Everybody's going to be a little bit
confused between the two armies. You've
got this large numbers of skirmishers
fighting their own little battle. He can
see what's going on there probably
better than the Romans can. Whether he
contributes to this at all or whether
the skirmishers and the officers with
them just do their job and they have
supports organized and all that sort of
thing. Very hard to say. But Hannibal is
in a better position than the Romans to
see what's going on. But it is still
quite difficult in a battle of this size
for any one man to be somewhere where he
can see all that's going on and be able
to respond to it.
>> Eventually, after what likely took
around 7 to 10 minutes of marching, the
leading Roman infantry units would have
come within striking range of the
Carthaginians cresant formation.
However, its echelon nature further
complicated the meeting of the two
armies. Presumably,
fighting would have begun among the most
protruding units where Hannibal and his
brother directly supervised the troops.
Here, battle likely took place in the
usual manner with the Romans charging
and launching their peeler at the enemy.
Likewise, the GIC and Iberian infantry
on the receiving end of the attack also
charged at the last moment with their
own flurry of missiles.
But what happened to either side of this
first contact point? This is where
things start to get even more confusing
with no clues offered from our sources.
Thankfully, the true size nature of our
model can offer some insight on the
matter.
>> One effect may have been that the
cresant blunted the force of the usual
Roman assault. By echeloning units
backwards, we see that as the Romans get
close to the line of first contact, the
Carthaginians are further and further
away. By the time you reach the edges of
the infantry, the gap is as large as 100
m.
For troops caught up in the momentum of
the charge resonating out from the
center of the cresant, having to cover
this extra football fields worth of
ground must have impacted their stamina
and psychology.
We know this was a serious issue to
consider. At the battle of Farcelus, for
instance, Caesar's troops actually
stopped mid charge to redress their
lines when they observed the enemy was
not advancing to meet them. On this
occasion, the veteran troops were able
to halt, reform, and re-engage for a
more optimal fight. At Cana, however,
the Roman army was far greener and
unlikely to have been able to pull off
such a feat. Thus, the troops at the
extremes of the line were likely faced
with suboptimal conditions.
With the extra distance to travel, did
they now run and arrive exhausted?
Did they throw their peeler too early?
Did they slow down and hesitate to
engage?
Unfortunately, we simply don't know. But
whatever occurred, the cresant seems to
have helped further delay and
disorganize the infantry attack. A
brilliant move on Hannibal's part to
counter Rome's greatest strength.
But no matter how blunted the legion's
charge may have been, the sheer weight
behind the assault meant that it was
only a matter of time before the Punic
line began to cave in. We are told by
our sources that this occurred in the
center here. Libby writes, quote, "This
wedge was first driven back so far as to
straighten the front and then continuing
to yield, even left a hollow in the
center."
Other sources back up the idea that the
Carthaginian cresant was inverted over
the course of the fighting. But how was
this achieved?
Palibius mentions the enemy giving
ground, which serves as a convenient
explanation.
But military historians have thrown much
doubt upon its feasibility. After all,
pulling off such a complex maneuver was
difficult enough on the parade ground,
let alone in the thick of fighting. Even
if one could perform such a thing, there
is the problem of doing so over a
significant distance without
disintegrating into a route.
To better grasp this issue, we can
simulate what Boeing the line actually
would have looked like from the ground
level. As hundreds of meters fly by, you
start to truly understand how great a
distance this is. By the time you get to
a 600 m full back point, you are likely
further away from the front than the two
armies were from each other at the start
of battle.
Thus, no matter the mechanism of the
retreat, it seems far more plausible to
assume that any inverting of the cresant
would have been far shallower than most
diagrams would lead you to believe.
That being said, we cannot definitely
rule out a large retreat or even a
breakthrough occurring.
But for our model, we have assumed a
shallow inversion.
As for how this was achieved, a
controlled retreat over such a small
distance does start to seem more
plausible, especially when we reimagine
what extended infantry combat may have
looked like. This is best explained by
Dr. Goldsworthy himself.
>> We do know that the Romans start to push
back the center of Hannibal's line. They
push back the crescent in the center,
perhaps break through it at least at
some point. How this occurs comes into
all sorts of questions about just how
ancient warfare, ancient infantry combat
did actually develop did actually
happen. The Hollywood image is everybody
runs together, fights individual jewels
and you know nearly everybody from which
somebody dies in all of these things and
then somehow they know they've won or
they haven't. Um real life isn't like
that. It's about groups. It's about um
units going forward trying to inspire
each other, officers trying to lead
them. So it fits more with the model
that people like Phil Sabin and I have
developed where you get bursts, pulses
almost of combat where because
hand-to-hand combat is physically
incredibly demanding and emotionally
demanding, but it's physically hard
work. You know, ask a fencer, martial
artist, boxer, someone like that, how
tired they get. Even somebody as highly
trained as that after short bouts of
combat, then add in the weight of
weapons and the stress that somebody's
actually trying to kill you. Then you
can't do this for 10 minutes, let alone
hours on end. It will be short bouts of
combat after which the two lines, two
sides separate. Perhaps only, you know,
the distance of 10 ft or so. That would
make them safe. maybe even less. If
you're outside the the distance anyone
can thrust a spear or stab with a sword,
then unless they've got something to
throw at you, you're safe. While you get
your breath back, you get your um
enthusiasm back and then you go forward
again, renew the combat. So whether
that's both sides step back, whether
that's one side steps back perhaps
because it feels it's not quite so
confident, not doing quite so well, you
do get mentions in ancient battles of a
side being pushed back a considerable
distance without apparently breaking and
running. So although that might be hard
for us to imagine within this context,
that seems to be fairly typical of a lot
of ancient infantry combat. You've got
lots of Roman leaders encouraging them.
You've also got Hannibal Mago, other
officers encouraging the Gauls, the
Aberians to keep fighting. So this does,
it is presented as a very hard struggle.
The Romans do not simply punch through
the center quickly. This takes time. And
again, we can look at the overall
casualty rate for Hannibal's army. It
does seem very high for a victorious
army, and the emphasis is that many of
your leaders go. Now, they're not all
falling at this stage, but it emphasizes
how hard this fighting is.
But all of this action in the center
would have taken time. Meanwhile, the
cavalry engagements which had begun
earlier would have been reaching their
climax.
Our sources claim that the action peaked
on the western flank first. Here we find
that the rolling cavalry engagement has
resulted in a ragged battle line. This
would have been particularly true around
the wings as the more numerous
Carthaginians attempted to outflank
their prey along the river's edge. Such
affairs would have been complicated by
the rushing waters and muddy banks, but
certainly there would have been some
messy fighting across such contested
ground.
Across the opposite side of the cavalry
brawl, the open fields would have
presented better opportunities for
maneuver. Here
we can imagine that cavalrymen
tentatively made their way through the
dust clouds, feeling out the edges of
the fo's formation.
Away from the pack, more isolated and
fluid fighting could have occurred
between individuals or small groups.
Crucially, Carthage's advantage of
reserves would have more easily allowed
them to exploit any vulnerabilities
which developed.
Eventually, the pressures along the
front and especially the envelopment
around the flanks would have cracked
Rome's morale. First as a trickle, then
as a deluge, riders broke away from the
fighting, fleeing for their lives.
With cavalry, such an affair would have
happened even faster than a route
amongst infantry.
Adrenalinefueled mounts now made for the
countryside,
perhaps hoping to make safe at the camps
to the rear.
Others, such as Consul Paulus, in the
case of Palibius's account, even
attempted to rejoin the infantry, but
Carthage was in hot pursuit.
As avenues of retreat were cut off, it
is likely that many desperate Romans
made way for the river.
Such a sight must have been incredible
to behold, as hundreds of troops now
spilled into the shallow waters. If our
sources are to be trusted, few made it
across alive.
Certainly, many Carthaginian squadrons
kept up the pursuit to drive the victory
home.
However, their commander, Hazdrabal,
acted with great skill and discretion by
reigning in many of his troops for a
charge across to the other side of
battle.
Such restraint is incredibly rare in
ancient battles, especially in the chaos
of a pursuit.
However, our model shows that this
action was likely made far more
practical by the use of reserves who may
well have been kept detached for this
very moment.
Now, such troops could have easily
wheeled into columns for an efficient
transit across the battlefield.
>> Viewed from the rear of the Roman
infantry, this decisive action might
have been glimpsed as an ominous
billowing of dust clouds moving against
the wind.
Meanwhile, on the eastern flank, the
indecisive fighting between the
Numidians and the Roman allies raged on.
>> Yet, amidst the indecisive fight, a
turning of the tides may have been
sensed by the observation of dust clouds
from the west.
The final revelation that these were
enemy reinforcements would have been
swift as their columns now fanned out to
envelop the pinned foe.
This pending disaster led to an
immediate collapse of the Roman
position.
Just as had occurred in the west, the
eastern flank now disintegrated.
From above, we can see this destruction
of the cavalry elements.
Once more, Hazdrabal shows great command
by sending off the Numidians in pursuit
while he himself rallies the remainder
of the cavalry to strike at the exposed
rear of the enemy's center. But this all
would have taken precious time.
Meanwhile, as we return to the fight in
the center, we see that the nature of
the fight has evolved.
The first major change is that the
Romans have pushed back, if not
partially broken through the
Carthaginian center.
The second change is that in the process
of doing so, their formation has lost
all cohesion.
On the ground level, we can see why this
might be the case. Here, individual
soldiers at the front have shifted
around in the process of fighting or
rotating in and out of combat.
Meanwhile, units further to the rear
have also lost order as they slowly
advance with the front lines or
naturally expand to fill gaps in the
formation.
This has had the effect of turning them
into a wholly unmanageable mob. But for
now, such a state proves viable enough
to still bully their way through the
Carthaginian ranks, which is only a few
dozen meters deep.
As they do so, we are told by our
sources that the Libyans on the wings
now swing in to strike them from the
flanks.
However, looking at our model, it is
difficult to understand how exactly this
will have worked. One option would have
been to simply turn to the side and
attack the units next to them, but this
assumes that there was an exposed flank
to strike at with no friendly forces in
the way.
Another option would have been for the
Libyans to commit to a grander maneuver,
walking nearly a kilometer to reach a
breakthrough in the center or to wrap
around the Roman rear.
Either of these would have taken a
considerable amount of time and control
to execute.
We shall let Dr. Goldsworthy shed light
on the matter.
Canai does seem to be unique in the way
the Libyans function. There are
sometimes troops kept back to be
committed later and of course at Zarma
he'll have three lines mirroring the
Roman deployment but it's not they're
not doing the same sort of maneuvering
that um these Libyans do at Cannai. The
deployment though is fundamentally
unusual because you've had these Libyan
troops, the pick of your troops in
reserve. For most armies, reserves
aren't really a big feature of what they
do. I mean, the Romans have them, the
standard triplex a three lines. Though
again, you could see this more as waves
rather than as true reserves. Only in a
few battles and only later do we hear
about sections of a second or third line
being taken off to do something else. a
kind of sephili for instance where
maniples in the rear are taken off to
deal with the collapse of the Roman left
flank. So again it comes back to that
sense that can is a unique situation.
The tactics there are not part of some
long-term plan that uh Hamlar and then
Hannibal have been toying with over the
decades and trying to perfect but it's
actually something that Hannibal has
come up with for this situation and
facing this particular Roman army. So it
meets the tactical requirements of this
particular problem. Much bigger Roman
army, loads of infantry, and maybe it
also has some sense of what the
battlefield is like, what space there is
that I can do this. It's very vague, but
it's there are lots of ways it could be
happening and we probably oversimplify
because again, we rush through the
tactic and we want it to happen really
quickly. We also tend to assume that the
battle is a fluid constant thing without
lulls in the fighting without delays.
Even in this breakthrough that the
Romans have come forward there are some
units still standing up against them at
least holding them a little way and the
Romans hesitate, rest, get their breath
back, come forward again and attack. All
the attacks later on will tend to
consist more of hand-to-hand combat
because as the battle continues, those
men with missiles have probably thrown
them. So you might have light infantry
supporting them, but they'll in the main
you're having to get the energy, the
motivation, the enthusiasm to charge
forward again, fight hand to hand, and
hope the enemy breaks. So there's a lot
more slog and attrition. Even with this
Roman success, we probably are wrong to
think of it as happening really quickly
and everybody rushing through and then
the Libyans somehow, you know, running a
4-minute mile or so to get up to in neat
formation to hit the Romans in the flank
and trap them. The whole thing is
probably a lot more gradual than we tend
to imagine and it may happen unit by
unit rather than each wing of Libyans
doing everything at the same time.
>> But however it happened, it seems that
the commitment of the Libyans helped
further stall the Roman advance which
had been on the precipice of a
substantial breakthrough.
Perhaps even at this late juncture, the
legions may yet have had the strength to
press on.
Yet, this is when Hannibal's cavalry
finally returned to the fight.
Joining them may well have been the
Punic skirmishers who go unmentioned by
our sources.
If it was indeed Hannibal's ultimate
plan to strike a decisive blow to the
rear, it makes sense for at least some
of these units to have wrapped around
the flanks to assist them on this
mission.
But even still, with cavalry and
skirmishes at the rear, there was a
nearly 2 km wide stretch of open ground
for them to somehow cover.
The scales involved are made clear in
our model and force us to contemplate
how this might actually have happened.
Once more, Dr. Goldsworthy will guide us
through this thought exercise.
So you've got your mass of legionaries,
mostly the heavy infantry, Hastardi,
Principari in particular at the back,
but you've also got the Velates. Where
have they gone? They've pulled back,
particularly if they've used their
missiles. So you're adding in lots of
other people into this mass of a crowd.
And again, under normal circumstances,
the heavy infantry could turn round,
form up, charge, and drive off the light
infantry. They probably won't catch
them, but they can keep them at some
sort of distance. But you can't do that
if there's lots of cavalry there because
then you're going to your formation is
going to break up. You're going to be
vulnerable to the flanks. As you charge
forward, you'll tend to scatter. It's
the sort of thing that happened at Khai
um in the first century BC where you can
try and drive the enemy off, but then
you end up as a knot of infantryman
that's either going to be shot by
missiles, hit by missiles that are
thrown, charged in the flank, charged in
the rear. So that combination of cavalry
and light infantry which we can guess
might be coming in closing in on the
Roman rear is a very formidable one in
these circumstances cuz the Romans are
not an organized battle line anymore.
Again this is something the model shows
well because you can get a sense of how
much area these cavalry could occupy.
Particularly again, think of them as
groups, troop sizes, squadron sizes, 50,
100, 200 or so. Lots of groups rather
than one or two big blocks supported by
light infantry that can form up with
some supports, but also with most going
forward as a skirmish line. And they can
move. They're not static. They can
charge in, they can pull back, they can
charge again. So, you're being worn down
and it's sapping the strength. The
probability is though and clearly the
figures afterwards show that some Romans
substantial numbers of them do break out
of this encirclement which again comes
back to this idea it's a very wide area
behind the Roman formation and the
cavalry don't seal it off completely.
some knots of men will break out
probably to be amongst the ones that
surrender in the camps afterwards and
some of the survivors you know people
like Scipio Africanistas they get out
somehow or other so it's never
completely sealed but it's very
difficult and dangerous to get out in
only small numbers and they will do so
only if they're very determined to stick
together and fight their way out not
fight their way uh to sort of stabilize
the line
>> thus we now arrive at the end of
tactical maneuvers of the battle. All
troops have been committed and their
fates sealed by the hours worth of
grappling between the two great
wrestling armies.
The end result is that the Roman army
has been pinned such that any observing
referee would call an end to the match.
But in war, there is no such arbiter.
So what can history tell us about the
fate of armies caught in similar
predicaments?
>> Now armies have got trapped and
surrounded before in other battles on
smaller scales and they've been um
sometimes shot down from a distance. You
know, think of the Spartans on
Spectaria. Uh much smaller action, but
nevertheless gives you an idea of how a
more numerous, more maneuverable group
can take out heavy infantry. There have
been these disasters. There have been
mass slaughters in particularly some of
Alexander's victories over the Persians
where at Isus at Ga Cam even the think
of the um the Greek mercenary infantry
and the other Persian infantry at the
battle of the Granicus where they
effectively get abandoned by their
cavalry that's been driven off. They get
surrounded and they're wiped out. 2,000
are taken prisoner, allowed to surrender
and sent back in chains to slave in the
mines. Uh but the rest just slaughtered.
Alexander loses a horse um while he's
he's leading. There is still fighting
going on, but it is very one-sided. The
casualties are overwhelmingly suffered
by the beaten army, by the um the
mercenaries and the other Persian
troops, how many there are there. So,
these sorts of things have happened, but
never quite as deliberately as it can.
>> As Dr. Goldsworthy suggests there is
indeed a uniqueness to the nightmared
cana which ensued.
We can drop down to the point of view of
a Roman soldier for perspective.
Ancient authors shed some light on the
matter with brutal anecdotes of trapped
soldiers so tightly packed that they
could no longer lift their weapons to
defend themselves. While others buried
their heads in the sand to hasten their
own demise.
On top of this, we must add the
undocumented toll that heat, exhaustion,
and deadly crowd surges must have had on
the mob of Romans caught in the ever
tightening vice grip of the
Carthaginians.
Yet, even with all the attrition they
had endured so far, the legions still
represented a body of troops far more
numerous than the Carthaginians who
surrounded them.
This posed a unique logistical problem
for Hannibal's men on how to actually
dispose of their trapped foe.
What you have to remember is that the
50,000 or so Romans and Italians that
die in this phase of the battle have to
be killed at very short range by muscle
powered weapons. Some of them can be
shot down by sling bullets. They can be
hit by thrown javelins, other missiles,
but most you're going to have to go
forward and within arms length, within
that distance, kill them with sword,
with spear, with any other weapons.
The story of Canai is one of great
tactical subtlety, skill, but also of
extreme brutality. This is a very nasty
encounter. This level of slaughter in
this area is probably amongst the most
vicious and um costly of all ancient
battles focused in such an area. The
pursuits after Alexander's victories
tend to be spread out over a little bit
longer though you still get the
nightmarish stories of sort of bridging
the Isus with corpses much as you'll get
the stories of the affidious being
bridged with corpses. There's this
theme. There is a sense, yes, a lot of
the sources from Libby, Yappy, and the
like get a bit carried away, but the
nightmarish element probably is a
reasonable reflection of just what this
was like.
You have to be killed close up and it
has to be done by muscle power. And
those Romans don't just die, though.
They they are again suffering far
heavier losses because they're not an
organized fighting line. They're just
masses of desperate, terrified men. um
some of them fighting to the end, some
of them perhaps giving in. Um but all
having to be killed one by one. This is
probably lasting hours to kill all these
people because the Carthaginians are not
machines. They can't keep fighting.
They've got to rest and then go forward
again. And every time that's going to be
harder, their swords will be blunted.
You know, we have the the grim statement
attributed to Hannibal that at Zama, he
thought his front two lines would would
take the edge off the Roman swords and
weapons before they reached his veterans
who could show them. But that is
actually true. You know, the edges on
these things, all of this is driven by
muscle power. The more they strike into
flesh, into bone, into muscle, the more
they strike armor, the blunted they're
going to get and the harder it will be
to drive them home. So, it's grim, it's
appalling, it's very gruesome. But
that's the nightmare of Canai is this
mass mass slaughter.
By the time the sun began to set on the
battlefield, the final tally of
destruction was staggering.
Over 50,000 men lay dead or dying in an
area little more than a few square
kilometers across.
More than half the Roman army had
fallen, including a console, two
proconsuls, 29 military tribunes, 30
senators, 300 nobles, and many more
souls whom the history books do not
tally.
Even Hannibal suffered losses as high as
8,000 or roughly 16%.
An exceptionally deadly percentage for a
victorious army.
To this day, CA remains one of the
bloodiest single days battles in
history.
The fallout from this event is best
covered in another video. For now, we
will bring our own discussion to an end.
Looking back on this exercise of
modeling CA and true size, we hope that
it has given you a better understanding
of what happened on that day. Both from
the perspective of how ancient armies
deploy, maneuver, and fight, but also
from the perspective of the individuals
involved whose human experience should
not be overlooked and whose
understanding is vital for properly
bringing the past to life.
A huge thanks again to Dr. Goldsworthy
for helping develop this detailed model
of CANA and for coming on as a speaker
in this series.
If you enjoy our work, consider
supporting us on Patreon to participate
in polls, catch script previews, and get
HD downloads of all our art. We owe a
huge debt to our current patrons for
funding the channel, and to our
researchers, writers, and artists for
making this episode possible. We
certainly couldn't have done it without
this team and this community. So, be
sure to like and subscribe for more
content and check out these other
related episodes. See you in the next
one.